<Document><Content>THE BRAND.
THE BRAND.
THE BRAND.
Brand Identity Style Guide
June 2023Brand Identity
Style Guide
University Seal .............................................................................. 15Logos and Marks ........................................................................... 4
Clear Space and Minimum Sizes .................................... 6
Logo Downloads ........................................................................ 7
Logo Infractions ........................................................................ 10
Unit Logos .................................................................................... 12
Guidelines for Student Use ............................................... 14
Typography and Fonts ........................................................... 21 Accessibility ................................................................................... 24
Photography ................................................................................. 30
Color Palettes ................................................................................ 17
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
2THE BRAND.
THE BRAND.
THE BRAND.
What is a style guide?
A well-developed style guide is an essential tool for establishing a brand&#8217;s  
identity. It acts as a key document that helps designers and content creators 
communicate consistently with our audiences, so it&#8217;s a great asset for creating 
the most effective, on-brand content. 
This brand style guide outlines U-M&#8217;s design standards for professionals (both  
on and off campus) who do marketing and communications work for university 
schools, colleges, departments and programs. It includes guidelines for the  
applications and variations of our logos, color palettes, typography (font families, 
sizes, kerning and line height/spacing) and photography.
Why is it important?
Having a document to reference for expected standards makes the lives of 
designers and developers much easier and gives them a solid framework to use 
for their work. Providing and following brand standards ensures that all of our 
content distinguishes the U-M brand from its competitors across the board. 
This cohesion helps establish a strong brand identity that resonates with our 
audiences &#8212; reinforcing both brand awareness and loyalty.
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
3University Logos/Marks
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
4University of Michigan has four official marks &#8212; the primary logo, the horizontal logo, the  
secondary mark and the University Seal. The primary and horizontal logos  &#8212; which clearly spell 
out &#8220;University of Michigan&#8221; &#8212; are used for marketing/communicating to general audiences.  
The secondary mark (the Block M) is reserved for internal audiences or those already familiar 
with the university. The University Seal is strictly reserved for presidential and regental use. 
The primary logo is the main identifier for the University of Michigan. The primary logo, 
horizontal logo or a unit logo must appear on all publications, websites and other visual 
communications developed by U-M for external audiences.
The University of Michigan logo was carefully designed based on the proportions of the  
copyrighted Block M. Each element was sized, placed and colored for maximum visibility and 
legibility.
&#8226; Do not modify the size, position, color or relationship of any of these elements.
&#8226; Use only official, unaltered university logos/marks and unit logos designed to approved 
specs. Do not recreate logos/marks.
&#8226; Only use University of Michigan logos/marks on official communications, partnerships and 
sponsorships. U-M does not generally allow use of its logos/marks for projects not affiliated 
with the university, other than commercial products licensed through IMG Licensing, U-M&#8217;s 
licensing partner. 
The university&#8217;s unit logo generator allows designated U-M employees to create unit logos for 
their school, college, or department. Unit logos are made up of the Block M (the &#8220;secondary 
mark&#8221;) and the individual unit name.
Contact your unit&#8217;s &#8220;logo gatekeeper&#8221; to request logo files, or email idstandards@umich.edu for 
help.University Logos/Marks
PRIMARY LOGOHORIZONTAL LOGO
SECONDARY MARK  
(AKA: BLOCK M)
UNIT LOGOUNIVERSITY SEAL  
(FOR PRESIDENTIAL &amp; 
REGENTAL USE ONLY)
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
5Maintaining Clear Space
Always position the logo for maximum impact and give it plenty of room to help to ensure  
visibility and legibility.
The minimum clear space for the University of Michigan logo is defined as twice the height of 
the block serif. Understanding the clear-space rule is essential, as it is also the standard for logo 
position and scale on most printed communications. In that regard, the clear space rule should 
be maintained as the logo is proportionately enlarged or reduced in size.
A note about taglines. A tagline or other messaging may be placed near the logo as long as the 
clear-space guidelines are upheld. Taglines or additional messaging may not be &#8220;locked up,&#8221; or 
attached, to a logo.U-M Logo Guidelines
Minimum Sizes
When reproducing the primary logo, be conscious of its size and legibility &#8212; a signature that 
is too small doesn&#8217;t serve any useful communication function. The primary logo should never 
appear less than 3/4&#8221; tall in printed materials, and no less than 75 px tall in the digital realm.  
A logo signature may be reduced 3/8&#8221; tall in print, and 36 px digitally.
Print: 3/4" 
Web: 75 pxPrint: 3/8" 
Web: 36 pxx = internal breathing space  
based on the size of the serif
2x = external safe space to aid 
readability and ensure no 
other graphic becomes visually 
attached  to the official identity2x = external safe space to 
ensure nothing comes 
close enough to make the 
Block M look like part of a 
larger graphic
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
6We&#8217;re proud of our primary logo and secondary mark and want to ensure that they are used 
appropriately. There are various logo/mark kits available for download on the brand website, as 
well as  guidelines for their use.
For more information, contact idstandards@umich.edu.
Primary Logo Kit
What&#8217;s included: Six versions of the logo, each one provided in three formats:
A CMYK eps for print, a PMS eps for print, and a HEX png for digital. You can also download each 
file individually.Logo Downloads
Primary Logo: Use this 
version of the primary logo 
for 4-color applications (or 
2-color printing on white).Primary Logo with outline: 
This primary logo has a thin 
white rule around the edge. 
Use it when placing the 
logo on a dark background.
Blue Logo with outline: 
This blue-and-white version 
of the primary logo should 
be used when only one of 
the university&#8217;s primary 
colors is available and 
placing the logo on a dark 
background.Blue Logo: This blue-
and-white version of the 
primary logo should be 
used when only one of the 
university&#8217;s primary colors 
is available.
Black Logo: This black-
and-white version of 
the primary logo is used 
for applications like 
newspaper advertising.Black Logo with outline: 
This black-and-white 
version of the primary logo 
is used for applications like 
newspaper advertising and 
placing the logo on a dark 
background.
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
7Horizontal Logo Kit
What&#8217;s included: Four versions of the logo, each one provided in three formats:
A CMYK eps for print, a PMS eps for print, and a HEX png for digital. You can also download each 
file individually.
Secondary Mark (AKA: Block M) Kit
The secondary mark kit includes a CMYK eps for print, a PMS eps for print and a HEX png for 
digital.Logo Downloads
Full Color: The horizontal logo is for use only when vertical space is at a premium and horizontal 
layout fits better with design.
Reversed: The reversed versions of the horizontal logo is for use on dark backgrounds.
Black: This black-and-white version of the horizontal logo is used for applications like 
newspaper advertising.
The secondary mark, or Block M, is for non-retail use only.
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
8Examples of the Primary Logo in UseLogo Downloads
Primary Logo
Black LogoPrimary Logo with Outline
Black Logo with Outline
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
9Guidelines: Primary Logo
You may not alter the logo in any way. Specifically:
Guidelines: Secondary Mark (Block M)
You may not alter the mark in any way. Specifically:
Reproducing Logos with Limited Color
Ideally, logos would always be reproduced in full color. But when that&#8217;s not possible, maintain-
ing adequate contrast between logo and background is paramount. When working against a 
light background, one-color logos may be reproduced in Michigan Blue or black. Dark back -
grounds can support Michigan Maize or white logos to maintain acceptable contrast.
Guidelines: Blue Block Ms
Blue Block Ms are allowed, but are not recommended: the preferred colors for the Block M are 
maize, black and white. Email idstandards@umich.edu for more information.Logo Infractions
DO NOT replace the 
official typeface with  
any other
DO NOT use any part 
of the mark as part of 
another word*
*A single exception was made for the use of the Block M in the word &#8220;home&#8221; in the phrase 
&#8220;welcome hoMe&#8221;DO NOT modify, redesign, redraw, animate, distort  
or alter the proportions of the logo
DO NOT modify, redesign, redraw, distort or  
alter the proportions of the markDO NOT  add words, images, or other design elements or 
effects to the logo, or add the logo to another graphic
DO NOT  add words, images, or other design elements or 
effects to the mark, or add the mark to another graphicDO NOT  modify the size or position relationship  
of any element within the logo
DO NOT  rotate or render the logo three-dimensionally
DO NOT  rotate or render the mark three-dimensionally
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
10Most official schools, colleges and units of U-M are eligible for branded unit logos.
Using non-branded graphics is only allowable for limited-time purposes such as one-
time conferences or other events, or for specific time-limited initiatives (eg the university&#8217;s 
Bicentennial mark).
It&#8217;s important to use branded logos in all marketing communications materials, including but 
not limited to websites and other digital media, signage, ads and print collateral. Leveraging 
U-M&#8217;s trademarks strengthens marketing outreach efforts, and helps ensure that institutional 
messaging is cohesive.
No other graphic should ever replace an official branded logo.Logos vs. Graphics
Co-Branded Logos
Occasionally, the university partners with outside entities, creating a need for a &#8220;co-branded&#8221; 
logo presence.
The following guidelines have been developed for this situation.
For general use:
&#8226; The U-M primary logo should be positioned first, followed by the partner logo
&#8226; There must be clear space equaling the width of the logo between the U-M and partner 
logo
&#8226; There should not be any graphic elements in the clear space between the two logos
For use where space is limited:
&#8226; The Block M should be positioned first, followed by the partner logo
&#8226; There must be clear space equaling the width of the Block M between the Block M and the 
partner logo
&#8226; There should not be any graphic elements in the clear space between the two logos
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
11Unit Logos
The University of Michigan&#8217;s identity system is designed to create and maintain unity &#8212; to ensure 
that no matter what campus, college or unit is issuing the communication, it is properly and 
strongly branded. 
U-M units and external vendors are not authorized to create or modify university logos.
 
Formal Unit Logo
In this most formal signature, the top line identifies the unit to which the featured unit reports. 
This is typically used in formal communications when this institutional hierarchy is important.
Marketing Unit Logo
In situations where internal hierarchy is not important to the audience, this unit logo helps 
schools, colleges and other U-M units stand out.
Informal Unit Logo
As the title suggests, this mark is intended for informal representation of a unit. Linking the unit 
directly to the Block M without the addition of &#8220;University of Michigan&#8221; should be reserved for 
internal communications or for outreach to stakeholders who are already familiar with the unit.
Stacked Unit Logo
This log is typically reserved for settings in which there is limited space and the preferred 
horizontal logo would be less legible. This signature may mimic the hierarchy of the formal unit 
logo or the familiarity of the marketing unit logo.
Reproducing Logos with Limited Color
Ideally, logos would always be reproduced in full color. But when that&#8217;s not possible, 
maintaining adequate contrast between logo and background is paramount. When working 
against a light background, one-color logos may be reproduced in Michigan Blue or black. Dark 
backgrounds can support Michigan Maize or white logos to maintain acceptable contrast.
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
12Individual Students
Use of U-M marks by individual students is prohibited, with a few 
exceptions:
Current students and recent graduates may:
&#8226; use U-M marks on posters or presentations for conferences, as long 
as the work being presented was conducted at U-M
&#8226; order templated, pre-designed business cards produced by U-M 
Print Copy Mail or any Ann Arbor FedEx/Kinko&#8217;s locations 
Students may not:
&#8226; create their own business cards, nor may they use the logo in their 
email signatures
&#8226; use the marks on resumes, cover letters or custom apparel
Sponsored Student Organizations (SSOs)
May : 
&#8226; use the Block M as a standalone graphic 
&#8226; use their sponsoring unit&#8217;s logo signature
&#8226; design their own logos employing Michigan Maize &amp; Blue, but not 
the Block M or any other U-M registered trademarks
&#8226; All use of U-M trademarks need to comply with the logo guidelines 
on the brand site
May Not:  
&#8226; use the Block M as part of their logo 
&#8226; use a slab serif letter &#8220;M&#8221; as a standalone letter
Voluntary Student Organizations (VSOs)
May : 
&#8226; design their own logos employing Michigan Maize &amp; Blue, but not the Block M or any other U-M registered 
trademarks
May Not:  
&#8226; use university trademarks or logos 
&#8226; use a slab serif letter &#8220;M&#8221; as a standalone letter
There is an exception for events covered by a University Event Sponsorship Agreement. With this limited 
sponsorship, a VSO may be granted permission to use university trademarks through their sponsoring unit for 
official business relating to the event.
For more information, contact the Center for Campus Involvement at 734-763-5900 or uminvolvement@umich.
edu, or read more about student org policies and copyright and trademarks on the CCI website.
Ad Hoc Student Groups
In addition to organizations registered through CCI, some schools and colleges also allow their students to form 
and join informal groups based within the s/c/u. The policies for these groups are similar to the policy for voluntary 
student orgs, above.Student Use Guidelines
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
13University Seal
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
14University Seal
The Seal of the University of Michigan is used as a formal insignia on official university 
documents and on materials produced for the U-M Regents and President. Each of the three 
campuses has its own seal.
The Seal is not a marketing logo. Use of the Seal for any purpose other than those listed below 
must be approved by the ID Standards team and the VP/Secretary of the University.
The seal is reserved for:
Regental/Presidential Materials
Stationery products, business cards, etc.
Colors: PMS 8640 (Metallic Gold) + 282 (Blue)
Official Documents
Diplomas, transcripts, certificates and similar materials related to official university business 
Colors: PMS 8640 (Metallic Gold) + 282 (Blue) 
(diploma printers, who use engraving inks, will match the PMS colors as closely as possible)
Public Safety &amp; Security
DPSS badges, apparel, vehicles, signage, etc.
Colors: PMS 7406 (Maize) + 282 (Blue)
Commencement Materials
Commencement and Honors Convocation programs, signage, lecterns and podiums,  
university academic flags, etc. 
Colors: PMS 7406 (Maize) + 282 (Blue)
Licensed Merchandise
Gifts and apparel offered commercially through the U-M&#8217;s licensing partner, IMG Licensing
A one-color version of the seal is available for special printing processes (e.g., embossing).  
Contact: idstandards@umich.edu.
The seal may not be used:
&#8226; for non-regental or -presidential stationery products
&#8226; for printed or digital marketing materials
&#8226; on websites (except regents.umich.edu)
&#8226; in social media messaging
&#8226; by students
PLEASE NOTE: The outdated 3-color Seal (with red detailing) should NOT be used.
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
15Color Palettes
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
16Color Palettes
COLOR PRINT WEB WEB ACCESSIBLE COMBINATION
Maize PMS: 7406
CMYK: C0, M18, Y100 K0#FFCB05
#00274CBlue (#00274C)
Yellow (#FFCB05)
White (#FFFFFF)Blue PMS: 282
CMYK: C100, M60, Y0 K60Aa
Aa
AaAa
Aa
AaOne Maize. One Blue. One Brand.
Maize and blue play a vital role in establishing a clear and powerful image and in defining the 
University of Michigan brand identity.
Accessibility Requirements
When designing for the web, all content must conform to the accessibility standards set by the 
university&#8217;s ITS accessibility team.
Based on Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG 2.1), the criteria for level AA requires a 
contrast ratio of at least 4.5:1 for normal text and 3:1 for larger text, greater than 24px or 19px and 
bold. The chart below provides approved brand color combinations that meet WCAG 2.1 level AA 
standards.
This quick-reference chart shows which colors provide enough contrast to be used as text 
against a light background, and which colors don&#8217;t have enough contrast to be readable as text 
but could be used as a background.
Primary Palette &#8212; Signature Colors
Our signature color palette of Michigan Maize and Blue creates a powerful differentiator for our 
brand. Using this palette appropriately and consistently creates an additional layer of distinction. 
Signature colors may be used extensively both for large areas of color and as accent colors.
PMS: 7406 PMS: 282
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
17COLOR PALETTES
Secondary Palette &#8212; Supporting Colors
The colors in our supporting palette were chosen to complement our primary palette of maize 
and blue, providing additional range to the brand experience. They work well as accent colors or 
as backgrounds behind typography or graphics, but should never replace the primary palette 
as the main color(s) of a design. NOTE: While these colors are recommended rather than 
mandated, we strongly encourage you to use them.
Painting your office? Download a PDF of Sherwin-Williams paint colors corresponding to the 
U-M color palette from the brand site.
COLOR PRINT WEB WEB ACCESSIBLE COMBINATION
White (#FFFFFF)
Black (#000000)Tappan Red PMS: 484
CMYK: C8, M92, Y100, K33
Ross Orange PMS: 1595
CMYK: C0, M71, Y100, K3#9a3324
#d86018Aa
AaAa
Wave Field Green
Taubman TealRackham Roof Green
Arboretum Blue
A2 Amethyst
Matthaei VioletPMS: 398
CMYK: C14, M6, Y100, K24
PMS: 326
CMYK: C81, M0, Y39, K0PMS: 5565
CMYK: C44, M12, Y34, K24
PMS: 660
CMYK: C88, M50, Y0, K0
PMS: 2603
CMYK: C72, M99, Y0, K3
PMS: 668
CMYK: C70, M77, Y7, K23#a5a508
#00b2a9#75988d
#2f65a7
#702082
#575294Black (#000000)
Blue (#00274c)Black (#000000)
Blue (#00274c)Black (#000000)
Blue (#00274c)
White (#FFFFFF)
White (#FFFFFF)
Maize (#FFCB05)
White (#FFFFFF)
Maize (#FFCB05)Aa
Aa
AaAaAaAa
AaAaAa
Aa
Aa
Aa
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
18Color Palettes
Secondary Palette &#8212; Neutral Colors
The colors in our supporting palette were chosen to complement our primary palette of maize 
and blue, providing additional range to the brand experience. They work well as accent colors or 
as backgrounds behind typography or graphics, but should never replace the primary palette 
as the main color(s) of a design. NOTE: While these colors are recommended rather than 
mandated, we strongly encourage you to use them. 
COLOR PRINT WEB WEB ACCESSIBLE COMBINATION
UMMA Tan
Burton Tower Beige
Angell Hall Ash
Law Quad Stone
Diag M Metallic
Puma BlackPMS: 7502
CMYK: C6, M14, Y39, K8
PMS: 451
CMYK: C21, M15, Y54, K31
PMS: PANTONE Warm Gray 6
CMYK: C14, M19, Y21, K39
PMS: PANTONE Warm Gray 11
CMYK: C26, M36, Y38, K68
PMS: 872
PMS: PANTONE Black 6
CMYK: C100, M79, Y44, K93#cfc096
#9b9a6d
#989c97
#80764b
#131516Black (#000000)
Blue (#00274c)
Black (#000000)
Blue (#00274c)
Black (#000000)
Blue (#00274c)
White (#FFFFFF)
Maize (#FFCB05)White (#FFFFFF)
AaAaAa
Aa
AaAa
Aa
Aa
AaAa
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
19Typography and Fonts
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
20Typography
Typography is a powerful tool. When used effectively, the right font commands attention, elicits 
emotions and above all creates a voice. It&#8217;s why typography is such an essential component of our 
brand&#8217;s visual identity.
A note about &#8220;Victors&#8221;: The proprietary Victors font, which was developed by Michigan Creative, 
was specifically optimized for the words &#8220;University of Michigan&#8221;; it was not designed for long-
form reading and therefore is not available for general use.
How to Choose a Typeface
Legibility
Legibility refers to the design of the typeface &#8212; the width of the strokes, whether or not it has 
serifs, the presence of novel type design elements, etc. It is easy to tell one letterform from another 
in a legible typeface.
&#8226; Choose typefaces with conventional letterforms.
&#8226; Choose typefaces with generous spacing.
&#8226; Choose typefaces with a tall x-height (the height of lowercase letters in relation to uppercase).
Readability
How your type is set, combined with the overall legibility of the font, yields a certain level of 
readability. In most cases, communication comes before style &#8212; form follows function &#8212; so 
resolve readability first.
&#8226; Choose typefaces that were designed for your purpose. If a typeface was designed for 
signage, it may not work well as the body copy in a book.
&#8226; Align text to &#8220;ragged right&#8221; for comfortable word spacing online to avoid &#8220;rivers.&#8221;
&#8226; Make sure the leading (the amount of space between lines of text) is greater than the point 
size of your typeface.
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
21Fonts
Font Recommendations
New : Atkinson Hyperlegible is the Braille Institute&#8217;s new typeface for the visually impaired.
Named after the founder of the Braille Institute, Atkinson Hyperlegible was developed specifically 
for readers with low vision. Read more about it in Print Magazine.
Atkinson Hyperlegible   The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog
fonts.google.com/specimen/Atkinson+Hyperlegible  
General Use typefaces:
IBM Plex super family   The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog
fonts.google.com/?query=ibm  
Montserrat  The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog
fonts.google.com/specimen/Montserrat  
Nunito Sans   The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog
fonts.google.com/specimen/Nunito+Sans  
Merriweather   The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog
fonts.google.com/specimen/Merriweather
Display Typefaces: 
Playfair Display   The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog
fonts.google.com/specimen/Playfair+Display  
Oswald   The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog
fonts.google.com/specimen/Oswald
PLEASE NOTE: The fonts listed here are all available free of charge. The University of Michigan 
does not have licensed fonts for use campuswide, so any additional typefaces desired must be 
purchased by the individual units.
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
22Accessibility
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
23&#8220;Accessibility&#8221; is the inclusive practice of designing so people with disabilities can engage 
equitably. That&#8217;s a large slice of the population: according to Census Bureau data, nearly 30% of 
people in the United States and about one in 6 worldwide have a disability.
As a public institution, the University of Michigan must comply with the accessibility standards 
set by WCAG 2.1  (Web Content Accessibility Guidelines). But making content accessible is also 
an essential part of our culture of inclusion at U-M, and another example of our commitment to 
diversity, equity and inclusion.
Digital Accessibility
Accessible technology has led to innovations like Siri, speech-to-text dictation, touchscreen 
devices and much more. It&#8217;s helped increase usability and user experience, and improved the 
quality of code. And accessible design often breeds innovative technology.
If you have digital accessibility questions, please contact accessibility  staff via the accessibility 
help form or check the Information and Technology Services (ITS)&#8217;s Accessibility webpage for 
Content Creators &amp; Presenters. If you would like to stay current on disability initiatives, there is a 
self-register digital accessibility community on campus you can contact. To register yourself for 
the group, please use the MCommunity web application.
Some content in this section was adapted from the ITS Accessibility website. 
Print Accessibility
Most people think of websites when they think of accessibility. However, we believe printed 
materials should also be created with accessibility in mind. And there are things U-M 
communicators can and should be doing to achieve that objective. Since the ADA does not yet 
provide guidance about print, the recommendations below are based on the best-practices of 
U-M accessibility and design experts&#8217;. 
Overall, we aim to create attractive, legible and readable materials to engage the widest range 
of users. This means considering accessibility throughout the design process and being open to 
requests for alternative versions.
 
The best way to ensure accessible print materials is to offer alternate modalities &#8212; electronic 
files, audio versions, Braille, large-print or alternate-contrast versions (such as low-contrast 
versions or reverse-contrast type versions) &#8212; and advertise the availability of those alternatives.
U-M has partnered with Allegra Marketing, Print, Mail to establish a process for creating 
accessible print documents. For guidance on preparing print files for conversion to pdf, refer 
to Allegra&#8217;s tip sheet for print accessibility. (Link to pdf)
You can also improve your print materials by following these guidelines:
FONTS
With so many different font styles, it&#8217;s impossible to pick a minimum size to ensure readability. 
However, the following general principles can guide choices and implementation of fonts that 
promote accessibility:
NEW: See the typography page of this website for information about Atkinson Hyperlegible, the 
Braille Institute&#8217;s new typeface for the visually impaired. You can also download the font for free 
from Google Fonts.Accessibility
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
24Legibility.
Sans serif is more readable: Use a sans serif font for the main body of text whenever possible. Serif 
fonts may be used sparingly, but avoid those with dramatic thicks and thins and exaggerated serifs. 
Fonts with large x-heights are easier to read. (X-height refers to the height of the lowercase x for a 
typeface. Typefaces with tall x-heights have better legibility at small sizes, because the white space 
within each letter makes it more legible.)
Minimum text size: 
&#8226; Body text: Use at least 12-point type for body copy when possible. If you must use smaller type, 
make sure it has a large x-height.
&#8226; Footnotes and photo credits should be no smaller than 8-point. 
&#8226; Leading: Set the space between lines of text (also known as &#8216;leading&#8217;) to at least 20-25% greater 
than the font size. If you use a 10 point font, the space between the lines should be at least 12 
points. Extra leading helps readers maintain their place and move smoothly through content.
Avoid italics and all caps. Be sure underlining does not connect with the bases of letters.
Avoid hyphenation. While primarily an issue for people with cognitive impairments, hyphenation 
can also be an issue for those with low vision.
Simplicity.
Number of fonts: A maximum of 2-3 fonts per page or document is recommended. Standardize 
the style of headings, subheadings, etc. For example, all headings should be in the same font, 
size, and color. All subhead level 1 should be the same. This makes it easy to identify sections of 
the document at a glance.
Set type flush-left/ragged-right, since using justified text can decrease readability. Optimum 
line length is 8&#8211;12 words (approximately 60 characters).
Contrast.
In general, use dark foreground text on a light background, or vice versa. Some studies have 
shown that legible white type with ample leading on a dark background makes for a more 
comfortable read. Either way, there should be at least a 70% difference in color value between 
background and text. 
Colors behind dark type should be no stronger than 20%. 
Use color contrast checking tools to test contrast against common standards like the Web 
Content Accessibility Guidelines 2.X Success Criteria 1.4.3 Contrast (Minimum). Do not rely on 
color as the only means of communicating information. Be sure to use alternative options as 
well, like symbols, patterns or additional text identifiers.
ACCESSIBLE DATA VISUALIZATION
When designing accessible data visualizations, many only think of red-green colorblindness; 
but there are many types of colorblindness, including monochrome and low vision. The color 
palettes below (nearly) meet the needs of all.
To create relatively-accessible charts and graphs, where color rather than pattern is necessary, 
the following data visualization palettes have a contrast ratio of at least 3:1 among adjacent 
colors, as described in success criterion 1.4.11 Non-text contrast in WCAG 2.1.
The Equity, Civil Rights, and Title IX Office (ECRT) has already made available downloadable 
template files in both Microsoft Office and Google Suite for four common graph/chart types 
using these data visualization color palettes.
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
25C M18 Y100 K0
HEX #ffcb05C20 M34 Y100 K1
HEX #d0a200C34 M46 Y100 K11
HEX #a27c00C42 M57 Y100 K31
HEX #785700C47 M67 Y97 K56
HEX #523300C50 M80 Y76 K76
HEX #380900C100 M60 Y0 K60
HEX #00274cC90 M75 Y31 K16
HEX #2f4972C73 M56 Y19 K2
HEX #576e9aC52 M36 Y4 K0
HEX #7f95c4C31 M19 Y0 K0
HEX #a9bfefC13 M2 Y0 K0
HEX #d8edffAngell Hall Ash
C14 M19 Y21 K39
HEX #989c97Michigan Blue
C100 M60 Y0 K60
HEX #00274cMichigan Maize
C0 M18 Y100 K0
HEX #ffcb05Tappan Red
C8 M92 Y100 K33
Hex #9a3324A2 Amethyst
C72 M99 Y0 K3
HEX #702082Wave Field Green
C14 M6 Y100 K24
HEX #a5a508Qualitative Data Visualization Palette
This palette is designed for data visualization that is categorical in nature. Each color will 
represent one category in a set with no inherent order, such as race or gender. 
&#8226; Using the Color Contrast Analyser , contrast was tested between adjacent colors using Coblis
&#8226; The &#8220;Recommended Sequence&#8221; is the most ideal order to ensure all colors have sufficient 
contrast with neighboring colors. Sequences may be slightly adjusted if the pairs of colors in 
the &#8220;Contrast Errors&#8221; column are not adjacent.
&#8226; The &#8220;Contrast Errors&#8221; list bad pairings.
6-Color Data Visualization Palette (Recommended Sequence)
Contrast Errors (Avoid using these colors next to each other)
&#8226; Tappan Red / Angell Hall Ash
&#8226; Michigan Maize / Angell Hall Ash / Wave Field Green
&#8226; Michigan Blue / Tappan Red / A2 Amethyst
&#8226; Angell Hall Ash / Wave Field Green
Sequential Data Visualization Palettes
Sequential charts are used for inherently ordered or numeric values.
These colors do not reach the 3:1 contrast ratio with their neighbors. However, overemphasis on 
contrast can cause accessibility issues when reading inside the visualization itself. Therefore, 
a higher range of shades used within a single-hue palette may be more accessible (Source: 
Accessibility and The Sequential Palettes, A Case Study on IBM&#8217;s Color Palettes).
The blue palette is better suited for white backgrounds. The maize is better on black. Use a white 
or black background versus color to increase contrast with most shades in the sequential palettes.  
These sequential palettes were validated to be colorblind-friendly with Chroma.js.
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
26DESIGN
Readability.
Paper choice: Bright white paper can produce excessive glare. Choose a dull-finish, smooth 
paper heavy enough to prevent showthrough if your piece is two-sided.
Limit decorative fonts and type-on-path text elements. Make sure any words treated 
decoratively are repeated within the main body of text.
Try to avoid placing text over photographs, illustrations or other busy backgrounds. It can be 
difficult to ensure enough contrast against non-solid backgrounds.
Simplicity.
If folds are necessary, they should be simple and intuitive, like the popular folds shown here.
Content organization and structure: Keep the organization of content straightforward. Use 
headings to break up copy and enhance comprehension. Make sure headings are descriptive of 
the text following them.
Ensure paragraphs have consistent letter spacing and word spacing. Set type flush-left/ragged-
right; justified text can decrease readability. Optimum line length is 8&#8211;12 words (approximately 
60 characters).
Avoid visual clutter and maximize white space. People with low vision and those with cognitive 
disabilities benefit from ample white space. Diverging Data Visualization Palette
Diverging visualizations represent two extremes that meet in the middle at a neutral or 
meaningful value, or acceptable threshold (e.g. zero, passing, etc.)
Diverging visualizations represent two extremes that meet in the middle at a neutral value.
This diverging palette was created and validated to be colorblind-friendly with Chroma.js.
Other Recommendations to Consider
Divider Lines
Use divider lines between 
colors to help define their 
shape.Labels Directly on Chart
Label charts near the 
category rather than solely on 
a legend.Textures and Patterns
Textures and patterns 
increase accessibility of data 
visualizations.C M18 Y100 K0
HEX #ffcb05C1 M11 Y61 K0
HEX #ffde7cC0 M4 Y27 K0
HEX #ffefc1C34 M25 Y15 K0
HEX #aab0c0C71 M57 Y31 K9
HEX #5a6784C100 M60 Y0 K60
HEX #00274c
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
27LANGUAGE
Read more about language on the brand site&#8217;s editorial resources page.
Simplicity.
Know your audience. Write for them, not for the experts. There are many resources that can 
help, including Writing Clearly and Simply by WebAIM.  In general:
&#8226; Keep the message short and simple.
&#8226; Use short sentences, paragraphs and sections.
&#8226; Avoid complex words and sentences.
&#8226; Avoid acronyms entirely, but if that&#8217;s not possible, define and/or spell them out at least once 
in the content, generally at the first mention.
&#8226; Steer clear of &#8220;internal speak&#8221; and confusing jargon. Use words your audience will 
understand and relate to.
&#8226; Shorten and clarify complex material. 
&#8226; Add white space. People with low vision and those with cognitive disabilities benefit from 
ample white space.
Break up copy using headings to help readers navigate through content. Headings should be 
descriptive of the text that follows them.
Use the active voice instead of the passive.
PLANNING
Welcome Accessibility.
The University of Michigan values diversity in all forms. It is up to us to create a culture of caring 
and accountability around accessibility. Create plans for providing alternatives, and processes 
that members of the community can follow to request accessible materials.
Increased Budget.
Plan for adequate paper size and stock, high-quality images, alternate formats and the extra 
time and funding needed for creating additional formats.
Extended Schedule.
Allow sufficient time for the creation of alternate formats &#8212; including proofing and review by an 
accessibility expert.
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
28Photography
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
29Photography
A picture is worth&#8212;well, you know the rest.
Good photography is an integral part of our visual style. Photographs should embody our brand
personality, capturing the University of Michigan spirit and the prestigious nature of the
university. Photos should be expressive, evocative and compelling, communicating our
creativity, diversity and commitment to global outreach.
Michigan Photography is dedicated to capturing the essence of U-M through the people, the
events and the spirit that make Michigan great. Contact them today at 734-764-9217, 
umphotography@umich.edu or visit their website at photography.umich.edu to schedule a shoot.
Note: External businesses may not use photos of Michigan Stadium in their advertising without 
obtaining permission from Learfierld, our media rights holder, as the use of Michigan Stadium 
photos can create an implied association with Michigan Athletics. For more information, contact 
the U-M&#8217;s Licensing Office
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
30Reinforcing Safety in Photos
Safe Research, Smart Research: 
Reinforcing a  culture of safety in media
In 2015, President Mark Schlissel introduced a plan to enhance the culture of safety in  research at 
the University of Michigan. One area of focus in the plan is appropriate use of personal protective 
equipment such as safety glasses, gloves, and lab coats while in the laboratory. Continual visual 
reminders of best practices in the use of this equipment help to promote safe behavior in labs and 
other research settings, such as field research. 
When filming or taking photos of researchers at work, please be attentive to this concern. You can 
help to ensure the safety of researchers, others in the lab/field, and the work they are doing by:
&#8226; Reminding faculty, students and staff to wear their personal protective equipment, just as 
they would when working. 
&#8226; Setting shots so that the use of this equipment is visible, helping audiences to see it as a 
standard part of the research process. 
&#8226; Moving outside of the lab when you want shots such as portraits or informal groups, where 
the protective equipment would be a hindrance.
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
31Depicting Safety: What to Expect
Safety is everyone&#8217;s responsibility &#8212; this 
includes those behind the lens as well.
Basic considerations for research and 
laboratory spaces with chemical or physical 
hazards present:
Laboratories
&#8226; All individuals should be wearing safety 
glasses, whether doing work or not, 
when the setting depicts a laboratory 
environment or a situation where a 
hazard is present. 
&#8226; Gloves and a lab coat should be worn by 
anyone handling  chemicals. 
&#8226; No food or drink should be present. 
&#8226; Everyone in the shoot should be using 
personal protective equipment. 
Other Locations
&#8226; Appropriate personal protective 
equipment must be worn and protective 
barriers set in place when photos are 
taken in non-laboratory locations such 
as field work settings or &#8220;digs&#8221; that 
involve human/animal remains. 
&#8226; Appropriate equipment and barriers are 
required in many  settings to: &#8211; Prevent 
falls &#8211; Protect people in or near trenches 
that are not properly sloped     or shored &#8211; 
Protect people around hazardous 
equipment, on boats, on     roofs, and in 
similar situations
For general media-related safety questions or 
clarification about research safety images and 
videos, contact imagesafety@umich.edu.
When in Doubt&#8230;
The Environment, Health &amp; Safety team at 
the University of Michigan is available to 
provide advice and review  materials for 
individuals across campus. 
Visit ehs.umich.edu to learn more.PHOTOGRAPHY
University of Michigan Brand Identity Style Guide   |   June 2023
32MC220021
&#169; 2023 Regents of the University of Michigan  |  Produced by the University of Michigan Brand Office and designed by 
Michigan Creative, units of the Office of the Vice President for Communications  </Content></Document>